# Dana Ducharme

Baltimore, Maryland

dana.ducharme@gmail.com

603.986.2823

linkedin.com/in/danaducharme

## **Summary**

Result-driven engineering leader with extensive experience in computer science. Led large-scale enterprise projects and specialized tasks, involving all aspects of development, organizational improvement, program and project management, and team building.

Core competencies include Technical Leadership and Architecture, Innovation and Continuous Learning, Operational Efficiency and Process Improvement, Strategic Planning and Execution, Team Building and Talent Management, Cost Reduction, Security Leadership, and Customer Identity and Access Management.

### **Experience**

### **Director of Platform Engineering**

**Under Armour** 

Dec 2022 - Jun 2024 (1 year 7 months)

Supported an incredible team of over 50 infrastructure, mobile, web, logistics, analytics and backend engineers for Under Armour's global eCommerce websites, our digital MapMyFitness app and Customer Identity and Access Management (CIAM).

- · Led Solutions Architecture team which supported multiple teams across Engineering by providing architecture insights, setting and enforcing standards, reducing tool bloat and participating in quarterly planning.
- · Established and led Architecture Review meetings to support teammates with architecture and tooling decisions to improve consistency and reduce cost. Improved developer sentiment by 20%.
- · Reduced CIAM vendor costs by negotiating with our vendor to reduce costs by over 1 million per year.
- · Improved quarterly planning process as part of the leadership team which reduced planning time by 30%.
- · Established and maintained strong relationships with key external vendors, resulting in a 20% reduction in procurement costs and improved efficiency.
- · Administered common developer tools like Postman, Github, Atlassian Jira/Confluence and transitioned UA's entire engineering org from Slack to Microsoft Teams in less than 2 months.

## Senior Manager, Engineering – Platform

**Under Armour** 

Jan 2021 - Dec 2022 (2 years)

Led a team of over 20 developers in Austin, Baltimore and working remotely, in building and supporting the services behind MapMyRun, our connected fitness application used by over 60 million athletes.

- · Led the backend Engineering effort to separate MyFitnessPal application after its sale, which was completed in under 4 months by creating clear objectives and priorities.
- · Led a multi-million-dollar revamp of the backend of Under Armour's digital MapMyFitness app, increasing performance by 20%, reducing infrastructure costs by 15%, and reducing incidents by 60%.

- · Worked as a cross functional group to architect and build new features that help our users achieve their fitness goals. Led optimization of our backend codebase and reduced footprint by 30% while also adding new functionality.
- · Worked with a variety of programming languages (Java 8+, Scala, Go and Python), Kafka message bus and common data stores like DynamoDB and MySQL (RDS) to manage millions of daily transactions.

### **Engineering Manager, Engineering Advocacy**

#### **Under Armour**

Aug 2019 - Jan 2021 (1 year 6 months)

Improved Engineering org and the day-to-day life of our Engineers, by recommending and implementing tools and processes.

- · Discovered that we had built silos and had difficulty spreading knowledge. To tackle this, we overhauled our documentation, audited and documented our infrastructure and services, and built a culture of learning.
- · Improved developer satisfaction scores by 40%.
- · Built and organized a robust Tech Talk rotation where UA teammates and external technology leaders would present that had a streak of providing interesting content for over 2 years.
- · Managed our internal engineering tooling, reducing time to resolution by half.

### **Engineering Manager – Labs**

#### **Under Armour**

Jan 2019 - Aug 2019 (8 months)

At the direction of Engineering leadership, I was hand-picked as part of a small team, tasked with discovering and addressing problems not only within Engineering, but to provide Engineering support to other teams in the organization.

- · Organized and ran creative brainstorming workshops as well as interviewed dozens of teammates across UA and discovered that we did not have a good way to share and analyze our product data.
- · Built a proof of concept to allow users to view details about a product and provided insights.
- · Built relationships with parts of the business that Engineering rarely worked with in the past.

# **Engineering Manager - Quality Engineering, North America Ecommerce**

#### **Under Armour**

Feb 2017 - Dec 2018 (1 year 11 months)

Managed eight Quality Assurance, SDET, and Software Engineering teammates to deliver manual and automated testing for UnderArmour.com North America which was responsible for nearly \$.5 billion in revenue. Responsible for streamlining our testing strategy to allow more rapid development with a higher degree of confidence.

- · Transformed the team from mostly manual testing to a focus on automation and was able to cover 95% of our backend services and most of our frontend code.
- · Integrated automated testing into our CI/CD process, allowing our development teams to get testing feedback early in the SDLC process to be able to deliver with confidence.
- $\cdot$  Reduced time to market by 30%, reduced regressions by 80% and allowed our developers to push 25 releases a day up from 10.

### Tech Manager - UI / UX

### AOL Platforms (via purchase of Millennial Media)

Oct 2015 - Dec 2016 (1 year 3 months)

Managed a team in delivering UI for all projects in the Data Services group. The team successfully delivered dozens of products while working across multiple divisions of AOL using AngularJS, Bootstrap, LESS, Gulp, Karma, Jenkins and Docker.

· Led quarterly resource planning, process and standards development, continuous integration and automation.

### Tech Lead / Manager - Advanced Technology Group / Data Visualization

#### Millennial Media

Jan 2014 - Oct 2015 (1 year 10 months)

Led a team of seven developers responsible for delivering prototypes and products under the direction of the CTO, as well as other departments within Millennial Media.

- · Led a team that developed an interactive data visualization tool used to contextualize millions of mobile interactions using AngularJS, Node.js, Gulp, SASS, D3, Leaflet, Vertica, and Hadoop, generating nearly \$2 million in revenue.
- · Participated in org wide efficiency by spearheading an initiative to introduce automated testing into our CI/CD process, reducing time to market by 40%.

### Senior Software Engineer - Labs / Research and Development

#### Millennial Media

Nov 2011 - Jan 2014 (2 years 3 months)

Part of a team reporting directly to, and executing the vision of, the CTO for a mobile advertising and monetization company. Helped deliver a self-serve client solution, mainly written in Javascript, that generated \$1 million in its first six months.

- · Conceived and developed multiple prototypes that eventually became full-fledged products.
- · Researched and presented new technologies and tools to tech leadership and the CTO and led their introduction to the larger Engineering group.

#### Senior Web Developer

Cygnus Business Media

### **Lead Open-Source Developer**

The Atom Group

#### Lead Developer / Web Manager

Iron Labs, Inc.

#### **Web Manager**

Millennium Medical Communications, Inc.

#### Software Engineer

Agamatrix

# **Senior Web Developer**

Glen Group, Inc. / Drive Brand Studios

# **Web Manager**

NCIA

# **Education**

# **University of New Hampshire**

Bachelor, Electrical Engineering w/ CS option